<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Science on Martin Proks</title><link>/tags/science/</link><description>Recent content in Science on Martin Proks</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 08:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/science/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Pachter et al., 2026 bioRxiv</title><link>/blog/2026/pachter-et-al.-2026-biorxiv/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/blog/2026/pachter-et-al.-2026-biorxiv/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The work of &lt;em&gt;Pachter et al.&lt;/em&gt;, focuses on porting well established &lt;a href="https://bioconductor.org/packages/release/bioc/html/edgeR.html"&gt;edgeR&lt;/a&gt; package to Python (edgePython) using Claude Opus 4.5, 4.6 and Codex. As described in the paper, the edgeR is a non trivial package supporting various functions used for differential expression analysis in genomics research. Due to Python&amp;rsquo;s popularity in data science, having edgeR natively available in Python ecosystem, would be highly beneficial for the scientific community. Although, there exists alternative solutions of combining/converting R and Python objects interchangeably,&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; they can be cumbersome.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Osteoarthritis could be treated in future with drug inhibitor</title><link>/blog/2026/osteoarthritis-could-be-treated-in-future-with-drug-inhibitor/</link><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/blog/2026/osteoarthritis-could-be-treated-in-future-with-drug-inhibitor/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A new research from Stanford showed promising results tackling osteoarthritis (degenerative joint disease) by inhibition of 15-hydroxy prostaglandin dehydrogenase (15-PGDH). They categorize this gene as gerozyme, meaning it increases its activity with age. The research shows that inhibition (down-regulation of signal) helps with &lt;strong&gt;rejuvenation&lt;/strong&gt; of the cartilage. The hope is that in future, simple drug treatment could help with restoration of cartilage targeting elderly population, post-surgery patients or ACL-like injuries. This could be huge for osteoarthritis since cartilage rejuvenation is primarily done with stem cells. So far phase 1 clinical trials confirmed safety of drug administration in mice.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>