<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Blog/Weblink on Martin Proks</title><link>/tags/blog/weblink/</link><description>Recent content in Blog/Weblink on Martin Proks</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2026 08:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/blog/weblink/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>[Weblink]: LLM Visualization</title><link>/blog/2026/llm-visualization/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2026 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/blog/2026/llm-visualization/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://bbycroft.net"&gt;Brendan Bycroft&lt;/a&gt; created &lt;a href="https://bbycroft.net/llm"&gt;an online app&lt;/a&gt; which visually walks you through architecture and steps of LLM models (GPT-2 small, nano-gpt, GT2 (XL) or GPT-3).&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>[Weblink]: Epsilon in AdamW matters</title><link>/blog/2026/epsilon-in-adamw-matters/</link><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/blog/2026/epsilon-in-adamw-matters/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;When training LLM, &lt;a href="https://sifal.social"&gt;Sifal&lt;/a&gt; shows that switching from default &lt;code&gt;eps=1e-8&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;eps=1e-10&lt;/code&gt; in AdamW optimizer can lead to better results. He showcases this on his toy example where default epsilon oscillates when searching for local minima compared to proposed one. However, this only applies when training is &lt;strong&gt;NOT&lt;/strong&gt; done with &lt;a href="https://docs.pytorch.org/docs/stable/notes/numerical_accuracy.html#reduced-precision-reduction-for-fp16-and-bf16-gemms"&gt;half-precision&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Klioui, S. (2026). The Epsilon Trap: When Adam Stops Being Adam. Sifal Klioui Blog. &lt;a href="https://sifal.social/posts/The-Epsilon-Trap-When-Adam-Stops-Being-Adam/"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description></item><item><title>[Weblink]: microsoft/BitNet</title><link>/blog/2026/bitnet/</link><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/blog/2026/bitnet/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A new paradigm shift from Microsoft called &lt;a href="https://github.com/microsoft/BitNet"&gt;BitNet&lt;/a&gt;, where the objective is to reduce speed and footprint of LLM models, by storing the LLM weights as 1bit. This is done during training, compared to quantization which fixes the weights post training. Authors report promising benchmarking with &lt;em&gt;BitNet b1.58 2B&lt;/em&gt; using only &lt;strong&gt;400MB&lt;/strong&gt; RAM and 29ms latency. It will be interesting to see where we will see these types of models deployed in future. Targets could be phones, IoT or privacy focused closed offline systems. For more in-depth details, I highly recommend watching &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WBm0nyDkVYM"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; great explanation by &lt;a href="https://www.patreon.com/JuliaTurc"&gt;Julia Turc&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>[Weblink]: Osteoarthritis could be treated in future with drug inhibitor</title><link>/blog/2026/osteoarthritis-could-be-treated-in-future-with-drug-inhibitor/</link><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/blog/2026/osteoarthritis-could-be-treated-in-future-with-drug-inhibitor/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A new research from Stanford showed promising results tackling osteoarthritis (degenerative joint disease) by inhibition of 15-hydroxy prostaglandin dehydrogenase (15-PGDH). They categorize this gene as gerozyme, meaning it increases its activity with age. The research shows that inhibition (down-regulation of signal) helps with &lt;strong&gt;rejuvenation&lt;/strong&gt; of the cartilage. The hope is that in future, simple drug treatment could help with restoration of cartilage targeting elderly population, post-surgery patients or ACL-like injuries. This could be huge for osteoarthritis since cartilage rejuvenation is primarily done with stem cells. So far phase 1 clinical trials confirmed safety of drug administration in mice.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>